<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Earnest call to family-catechising and reformation by a reverend divine.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E95</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31403</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11962395</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11962395</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39501)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1005:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Earnest call to family-catechising and reformation by a reverend divine.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], xix, 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.W. for John Dunton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51600:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EARNEST CALL TO <hi>Family-Catechiſing,</hi> AND REFORMATION. By a Reverend Divine.</p>
            <q>The Father to the Children ſhall make known thy truth, <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38. 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Children obey your Parents in the Lord, for this is right.—And ye fathers bring up your children in the nurture and admonition of the Lord. <bibl>
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 1, 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Woe unto thee, O Jeruſalem! <hi>[England.]</hi> wilt thou not be made clean? when ſhall it once be? <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 13. 27.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> J. W. <hi>for</hi> John Dunton, <hi>at the</hi> Raven <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey. 1693.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51600:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:51600:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WHoever thou art, that wilt condeſcend to read this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Piece, I think fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thee with whatever relates thereunto, from its firſt concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to its coming thus into the World. How the poor Thing will thrive now, and what Service this Stripling (of which I muſt ſay, Is it not a little One?) is born for, God alone knows, to whoſe Guardianſhip, and Diſpoſal I entirely ſubmit it.</p>
            <p>If thou art inquiſitive of its Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, know, it proceeds from a Stock, Spiritually very mean; and, in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſprings <hi>as a Root out of dry Ground:</hi> Yet he that made <hi>Aaron</hi>'s dry Rod to bud and bloſſom, and bring forth Fruit, can do ſo by this.</p>
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:51600:3"/>
            <p>The Author remembers ſomewhat of thoſe former Times, when the Reins of Government were not ſo ſlack in <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, profeſſing Chriſtanity,</hi> and when there was a more ſtrict, and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Education of Children, than in theſe licentious Days, in which many Parents out-do the <hi>Oſtrich</hi> in Cruelty, and are Spiritually <hi>hardened againſt their young Ones, as though they were not theirs,</hi> Job 39. 16.</p>
            <p>When the Foundation of the Second Temple was laid, the young Men ſhou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for Joy; but the ancient Men wept, becauſe the Foundations of the New Temple, came ſo much ſhort of the former, which they had known in its Glory, <hi>Ezra</hi> 3. 12, 13. Methinks I find a mixture of both theſe Affections in my own Soul, with reſpect to the private Families of Chriſtians, which ſhould be little Churches. I heartily rejoyce to ſee, or hear, even that little Meaſure of good Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is in any of them; and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, <hi>unleſs the Lord of Hoſts had left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us a very ſmall remnant, we had been as Sodom, and as Gomorrha, Iſa.</hi> 1. 9. But I ſee, abundantly, more cauſe of Mourning, in that the preſent Glory on Chriſtian Families, comes ſo much ſhort of the Glory of the former.</p>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:51600:3"/>
            <p>How deplorable is the perſonal Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of Multitudes, who ſhould be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and governed in Families! For, by reaſon of theſe Neglects, Satan hath made a great Harveſt of Souls, and Hell hath inlarged it ſelf, beyond Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But, beſides perſonal Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, how great Diſadvantages have hereby redounded to the Publick. There are little viſible Acceſſions to the Church, from Chriſtian Families. God's <hi>Orchard of Pomgranats,</hi> is meanly Stock'd from theſe Nurſeries: And whence ſhould the Churches Increaſes be primarily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but from thoſe on whom God hath laid ſuch ſpecial Obligations, and to whom he has given ſo great Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Moreover, much from the ſame Cauſe it is, that the preſent Age is ſo generally, and fearfully Debauched, that we may truly ſay, <hi>The whole World lyeth in Wickedneſs;</hi> and, <hi>all Fleſh have corrupted their ways:</hi> and take up the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s upbraiding Complaint over <hi>Judah, Ah ſinful nation! a people laden with iniquity! a ſeed of evil doers! children that are corrupters! They have forſaken the Lord! they have provoked the holy one of Iſrael to anger! they are gone away backward! The whole head is ſick! the whole heart ſaint! from the ſole of the</hi>
               <pb n="iv" facs="tcp:51600:4"/> 
               <hi>foot, even unto the head; there is no ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in it, but wounds and bruiſes, and putrifying ſores!</hi> Iſa. 1. 4, 5, 6. So that both Church and State are ſick at Heart, and utter dying Groans under this dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Malady, the Neglects of Family-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
            <p>It has been oft; and much upon my Thoughts, that as the preſent decays of Religion, and increaſes of Wickedneſs, have, in a great meaſure, come in upon us, at this breach, the neglect of <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Order,</hi> and particularly, as to <hi>Catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing;</hi> ſo it is ſome effectual revival of that Ordinance, that muſt lead the way to a thorough Reformation. But I have withal experienced, That there is a ſort of Catechiſing, which is next to nothing, that is, to teach a Catechiſm meerly by rote, without a familiar Explication, and home Application of it.</p>
            <p>We have Inſtances left us upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in Hiſtory, of the Churches exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Care of her <hi>Catechumens,</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages. And bleſſed be God, who hath raiſed up many worthy Miniſters, who have, in this our degenerate Age, born a great Teſtimony unto this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, tho' they did not live to ſee it grow ſo as they deſired. That Man of an <hi>Apoſtolick Spirit,</hi> that underwent ſuch
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:51600:4"/> Labours, and had ſuch Succeſs in carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel among the <hi>American</hi> Indians, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> John Eliot, <hi>of</hi> New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>ſee his Printed Life.</hi>
               </note> and was Inſtrumental of thoſe Stones, to raiſe up ſo many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto <hi>Abraham;</hi> has this remorable Notion on thoſe Words of our Lord. <hi>Feed my Lambs; feed my Sheep; feed my Sheep,</hi> Joh. 21. 15, 16, 17. <q rend="inline">That the Care of the Lambs, is one Third Part of the Charge over the Church of God.</q> A worthy and moſt intimate Friend, who did both expend a good In-come, and ſpend himſelf in the Works of the Lord, and is now ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto his Reward; I have heard declare, <q rend="inline">That if he could not Preach and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Brand.</note> Catechiſe too, he would rather omit the former, than the latter:</q> Such a Senſe he had, both of the need, and benefit of Catechiſing: Yea, and in his lingering Sickneſs, he continued Catechiſing after he had laid down preaching. A great Maſter-Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in his moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sermon on this <note place="margin">Mr. Lye, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> 2 <hi>l. in the Supplement to the Morning-Lectures at</hi> Cripplegate.</note> Subject, (which I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not that I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read till ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time after I had finiſhed the following Tract) gives
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:51600:5"/> in this great Teſtimony. <q rend="inline">Thoſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſms that were compos'd by the late Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> I have made uſe of both in my Congregation and Family, now near Thirty years, and I deſire to ſpeak it with all humility, and thankfulneſs, if ever the Lord ſmiled on my poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, it hath been while I have been buſied in this great, uſefull, neceſſary work of Catechiſing, and that out of theſe Catechiſms.</q>
            </p>
            <p>As God hath in our time raiſed up many worthy Men, who have laid to heart this Duty, and born their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony unto it: ſo they have likewiſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured abundantly for the promoting of it, and ſome have left their worthy Labours in Print, as a <hi>Legacy</hi> behind them: inſomuch that perhaps there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was an Age that had ſo many great and advantagious Helps for Catechiſing, as this of ours. And tho' neither the Practice, nor Succeſs has yet been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable; yet ſure it is not for nothing, that God has put it into the Hearts of his Servants to prepare ſuch ſtores of rich Materials. I hope it is a good Omen, that this Work, and the Succeſs of it, ſhall yet revive among us. <hi>David</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Materials, but <hi>Solomon</hi> built the Lord's Houſe. Herein may that Saying be true, <hi>One ſoweth, and another reapeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="vii" facs="tcp:51600:5"/>
            <p>It has been noted that there are of one kind or other, about <hi>five hundred Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms</hi> extant. The Reaſon why I more particularly recommend thoſe of our <hi>late Aſſembly,</hi> is not that I diſreſpect, or would oppoſe any good Catechiſm; but theſe are extraordinarily fitted for this purpoſe, have had the Eſteem of <hi>Foreign Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> as well as a general Reception here at home. Beſide our Diſſenters, many Members, yea, Miniſters of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> have approved of, and uſed theſe, as agreeable to the genuine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that Church. My Reverend Friend, whoſe Pen has given us ſome touches <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the printed Life of Mr.</hi> Brand, <hi>written by Dr.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſly.</note> on the Life of the greatly uſefull Maſter <hi>Brand,</hi> mentioning the Aſſemblies Catechiſm, ſaith, <hi>The Lord Primate of</hi> Armagh <hi>ſaid, It was the beſt extant.</hi> And what tho' this Catechiſm was among other good Books, not long ſince, ignominiouſly burned, even in one of our Univerſities; yet we need only conſider when, and by whom it was done. This Villany was perpetrated at a time when all our Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations Civil, and Religious, were out of Courſe; and by ſome wicked Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries, who ſerved that but as they did the <hi>Lord's Prayer, Commandments,</hi> and the <hi>Creed;</hi> which are not only incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:51600:6"/> with, but alſo printed at the end of the Catechiſm: And ſo, no doubt, they would have ſerved our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, had it been in their power. Theſe are not <hi>genuine Sons,</hi> but Monſters, that hang on the Breaſt of our Nurſeries of Learning. I likewiſe the rather pitch upon theſe Catechiſms; becauſe ſo many worthy Men have written Explications of them, (as I hint elſewhere,) which may be ſubſervint to our Uſe of them.</p>
            <p>I have, of late Years, where-ever I have had Opportunities, ſet up publick Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing, and have conſtantly obſerved it to produce evident Tokens of Good, both on Young and Old. And Elder People have thus expreſſed themſelves to me: <hi>We anſwer to our ſelves the Queſtions you ask the Younger.</hi> The Method I uſe in publick Catechiſing, is this, and I would be glad to learn a better. I firſt ask the Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens the Queſtions that I particularly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon in the Catechiſm, to prove their being perfect in the Anſwers. I then put further Queſtions to them, (ſuch as are in Mr. <hi>Lye</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Allein</hi>'s Explications of the Catechiſm,) to prove their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſence of the Anſwers: And finally, I ſumm up all with a more entire Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in which I endeavour to be Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, as well as Doctrinal. But this I muſt ſay, it is the <hi>Queſtionary part,</hi> I mean, putting particular Queſtions plainly and
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:51600:6"/> pathetically upon the Particulars contain'd in, or ſome way relating to the Anſwers. It is this, I ſay, that I have obſerved to do the main Execution. I have alſo laid to heart, the great Neceſſity and Benefit of <hi>Family,</hi> as well as <hi>Publick Catechiſing.</hi> And withal conſidering, that ſome might omit this, or not perform it to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; merely from inability to manage it effectually, and for want of Direction how they might profitably proceed with it: Hereupon I caſt it in my Thoughts, how a profitable Method might be propoſed, which might be moſt plain and eaſie, both to them that Catechize, and to thoſe that are Catechiſed in Families. Now the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of theſe Thoughts, is in that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little Treatiſe, which thou art here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with.</p>
            <p>When I had firſt drawn it up, I pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately communicated it to ſome few of that loving and kind People where then I was, and for whoſe ſake I writ it. I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſummoned the Heads of Families together, with their young Ones, and cauſed it to be read in their Audience, exhorting them to proceed in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies according to the Method which you have recommended under the <hi>Fourth Head</hi> of the <hi>Third Chapter.</hi> And ſince naked Rules are not ſo effectual for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, as thoſe that are back'd with practical Examples; I appointed ſeveral
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:51600:7"/> Meetings, for that purpoſe; and did, before them, Catechize their Young Ones, not according to the freedom I uſe in my publick Exerciſes of that Nature, but expreſsly according to that preſcribed Method. That is; Firſt, I began with <hi>Prayer.</hi> Then I asked the young People Three Queſtions out of the <hi>Aſſemblies Catechiſm.</hi> Next I interrogated them more particularly on the Anſwers out of Mr. <hi>Lye</hi>'s <hi>Explanation of the Catechiſm,</hi> (and the ſame, as I have intimated, may be done by Mr. <hi>Allein</hi>'s.) Then was read, out of Mr. <hi>Thomas Vincent</hi>'s Explicatory Catechiſm, what related to the Three Anſwers inſiſted on. After which, I briefly prayed. We ſung ſome part of a Pſalm, and ſo I diſmiſs'd them with a <hi>Solemn Bleſſing.</hi> Herein we experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally found a Preſence of God with us; as I doubt not but thou wilt do, <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou wilt, with thy Family, make Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. And I pray thee be not only a <hi>Reader,</hi> but <hi>Practitioner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this, ſeveral that were my Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers requeſted Copies of my Papers; which I could not deny them. Some, both <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>private Chriſtians,</hi> who have peruſed them, moved for their Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication: Which I have now condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to, though, at firſt, I only intended them for Private Uſe. In Tranſcribing, I have now divided it into <hi>Chapters,</hi> for
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:51600:7"/> diſtinctneſs ſake, which I had not done at firſt; and ſomewhat of Additions and Alterations I have made. The laſt Head of all, with the Concluſion, had ſome particular Aſpect toward that People for whom it was firſt pen'd; to whom God wonderfully continu'd their Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary-Enjoyments <hi>throughout a very dark and cloudy Day.</hi> You have it without the Alteration of what related to that Circumſtance. But I may here add now, That the more general Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that God has ſince that time ſo wonderfully wrought for theſe Nations, and which our Selves and Families are Sharers in, ſhould much more be an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Motive to this Duty toward God, our Selves and Families.</p>
            <p>And now, whoever thou art, that takeſt this <hi>little Book</hi> in hand, thou art the Perſon with whom its buſineſs is: <hi>Read, Conſider</hi> and <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any who are honour'd with the High Calling of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> ſhall vouchſafe to caſt an Eye on a thing ſo very mean. Let even theſe <hi>Fathers</hi> hearken to one Requeſt, from the very leaſt of all the Sons of the Prophets: In a time when too many are like dumb Dogs, that cannot bark; do you, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, like faithful Shepherds, rouze up your ſelves and your Flocks unto this Duty, that they be not deſtroyed for
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:51600:8"/> lack of Knowledge. Poſſibly you may adviſe to a much better Method than I have propoſed; which I ſhall not be offended at, but rejoyce in. As to that by me recommended, I only deſire, that all ſuch would uſe it, as have wholly neglected this Duty, or are acquainted with no better way of performing it.</p>
            <p>You that are <hi>Parents</hi> of <hi>Children,</hi> and <hi>Governours</hi> of <hi>Families,</hi> conſider the Souls committed to your Charge are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and ſhould be ſo to you. As the Talent is, ſo the Account will be great. <hi>It is worth while to perform Duty, though without Succeſs:</hi> Yet who knows what bleſſed Succeſs may attend <hi>ſincere,</hi> though <hi>weak</hi> Endeavours. You may thus, early, prevent thoſe youthful Extravagances, which, like Errors of the firſt Concoction in the Body Natural, once admitted, are ſeldom cured. If any belonging to your Families are in a <hi>courſe of Sin,</hi> who knows, but a little Advice, faithfully given, may be to them like the <hi>Remora,</hi> a little Fiſh, which (they ſay) if it ſtick to the greateſt Ship, will put her to a ſtop, when under full ſail? Admitting ſome be Angling for the World, thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Counſel may be like the <hi>Torpedo,</hi> which (it is ſaid) in a ſecret way tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth its Vertue to the Rod, and ſo to the Hand of the Angler, and makes him let it fall. Who knows, but by this means,
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:51600:8"/> thoſe of thy Family may be made know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, methodical, well grounded, ſteady, <hi>practical Chriſtians</hi> here upon Earth, and at laſt become glorious Saints in Heaven. What a Bleſſing had that good Man, who could comfortably ſay, <q rend="inline">I have had Six Children, and I bleſs God for his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Eliot, <hi>of</hi> New-England.</note> free Grace; they are all either with Chriſt, or in Chriſt, and my Mind is now at reſt concerning them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I can yet condeſcend to offer Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of an inferiour Nature, <hi>if by any means I may gain ſome.</hi> The Books recommended for your Aſſiſtance in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing, are very good, yet very cheap; very full, yet very brief; very deep, yet very plain. Theſe Catechetical Exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will tend to <hi>ſweeten the very Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the Family;</hi> they will mend the Diſcourſes of the Family, at other times. They will improve your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren's Underſtanding, advance Parts, and accidentally fit for Employments, in wordly buſineſs and converſe. This will tend to make them better Husbands, and to keep, uſe, and improve their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates the better. It will be a means of encreaſing <hi>Family-Love,</hi> and promoting Obedience. Your Children that are in danger to become Rods, yea Scorpions to you, may by this means become a
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:51600:9"/> Staff in your Hand. It is ſaid, <q rend="inline">That eminent Family in <hi>Rome,</hi> received the Name <hi>Scipio,</hi> from one of their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who was <hi>Scipionis vice,</hi> as a Staff to his Parents.</q> Such may yours be. The Regulation of Chriſtian Families, will give a Set-off to Religion, and commend it even to a carnal World. <hi>When the Queen of Sheba had ſeen the wiſdom of Solomon, and the houſe that he had built, and the meat of his table, and the ſitting of his ſervants, and the attendance of his miniſters, and their apparel, and his cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers alſo, and their apparel, and his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent by which he went up into the Houſe of the Lord: there was no more ſpirit in her,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10. 4, 5. In a word, by this means, may be raiſed up more accompliſh'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in Church and State, and both dearly need ſuch. You that are Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and the govern'd Part of Families, hearken to that Counſel, that out of meer good Will, is given you by one that wiſheth your Welfare here, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It has been obſerv'd by my intimate good Friend, who is now with God, <q rend="inline">How <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Joſeph Whiſton <hi>of</hi> Lewes, <hi>in</hi> Suffex.</note> the Privileges of the Infant Seed of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, has been aſſerted and pleaded for by himſelf, and ſome others, who had no Children.</q> So here you have the good of Children, and Families,
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:51600:9"/> ſought and endeavoured by one that hath neither Child nor Family. Do not hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the deſtroyer of Souls, and turn a deaf Ear to ſuch as deſire your Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Read with fear and trembling, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1. 20. to the end, <hi>Prov.</hi> 5. 11, 12, 13, 14. with other the like Scriptures. Many bewail theſe neglects, and the ſad conſequences of them, on the <hi>Rack of Conſcience on a Death-Bed,</hi> and ſome in <hi>Chains,</hi> and at the <hi>Gibbet:</hi> Yea Hell, in all the Caverns of it, is filled with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Echoes of the doleful Yellings of thoſe, who, in vain, torment themſelves with ſevereſt Reflections on their Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miſcarriages. If you will rant away your time and opportunities here, you alſo ſhall roar it out there to all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. God's Priſon will hold you, if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing will reſtrain you ſhort of it.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Grinaeus</hi> rejoyced, when he ſaw any young Perſons im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving, and was wont <note place="margin">Melch. Adam <hi>vit Thed.</hi>
                  </note> to ſay, That more worſhipped the riſing than the ſetting Sun.</q>
            </p>
            <p>O what great things may you do for God, your own Souls, and the ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Age: Others muſt quickly ſleep with their Fathers. The Children of this Age, muſt be the Men and Women of the next: 'Tis in, and with you, that Religion muſt live or dye. There is a
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:51600:10"/> Promiſe, <hi>Inſtead of the fathers, ſhall be the children, whom thou mayſt make princes in all the earth.</hi> Pſal. 45. 16.</p>
            <p>I have been beſpeaking no leſs of you, than to endeavour, after a truly ſanctified ſaving Knowledge: but if I muſt not prevail in that, yet let me de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to get, at leaſt, a notional Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and it may be, Grace may come afterward. And here I ſhall take leave to recover from Oblivion, a Paſſage that I do not know, is preſerved by any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Print. I have heard of one, who being Servant in a Family of good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, did, while there, ſubmit to <hi>Family-Catechiſing,</hi> and thereby obtained a form, tho' only a form of Knowledge. After his removal thence, he fell into ill Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and Courſes, and at laſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome Fact, puniſhable with Death: Being apprehended, and committed to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the <hi>Poor Creature</hi> at once ſaw Death and Hell before him, and began to bethink himſelf how, tho' he muſt loſe his Life, he might ſave his Soul. His time was ſhort, he was ſhut off from all Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges abroad, and ſhut up with Company, more like to harden, than ſoften his Heart. In the Multitude of his hurry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Thoughts within him, he begun at laſt to reflect upon that <hi>good Family,</hi> he once lived in, and he ſeriouſly recollected the good Things he then obtained ſome
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:51600:10"/> Notion of, and it pleaſed God, that his <hi>Knowledge iſſued in Converſion.</hi> And when he came to dye by the Hand of Juſtice, this was part of the good Advice he gave to thoſe who were Spectators, <q rend="inline">That they would get Knowledge, tho' they did no more, for that the Truths, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up in their Heads, might afterwards fall down on their Hearts. This, he ſaid, was his caſe, or elſe he could not with ſuch comfort, go thus out of the World.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let me in the cloſe importunately beſeech Magiſtrates, Miniſters, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Miſtreſſes of Schools, all Heads and Members of Families, effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to ſet upon promoting this, and other parts of <hi>Reformation,</hi> as they would eſcape thoſe moſt fearful Judgments, which will elſe, as certainly befall one, and all of them, as there is a Righteous God in Heaven, and wicked Sinners on Earth. God will <hi>pour forth his fury upon the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then that know him not, and on all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that call not on his Name,</hi> Jer. 10. 25. It is ſaid, <hi>of a people of no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that he that made them, will have no mercy on them; and he that formed them, will ſhew them no favour,</hi> Iſa. 27. 11. And let not the lucid interval of our preſent ſeeming deliverance, flatter any. <hi>The Proſperity of fools deſtroys them.</hi> The Sun ſhone on <hi>Sodom</hi> in the Morning, and yet God rained Hell out of Heaven
<pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:51600:11"/> upon it, e're Noon. God will not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us to do all our Abominations. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we repent, we ſhall periſh.</hi> It muſt be Repentance and <hi>Reformation,</hi> or Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and Deſtruction. In vain we flatter our ſelves with Peace, if God be our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and proclaim War againſt us. <hi>There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wicked,</hi> Iſa. 57. 21. But if we timely Repent and Reform, <hi>It may be we may be hid in</hi> (or <hi>from) the day of the Lords anger,</hi> Zeph. 2. 7. Saith the Lord, <hi>Wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall be the ſtability of thy times, and ſtrength of Salvation,</hi> Iſa. 33. 6. And, <hi>The Lord will create upon every dwelling place of Mount Zion, and upon her Aſſemblies, a cloud and ſmoak by day, and the ſhining of a flaming fire by night, for upon all the glory ſhall be a defence.</hi> As one great Step toward Reformation and Safety, <hi>God himſelf turn the hearts of the fathers to the children, and the hearts of the children to the fathers, leſt he come, and ſmite the earth with a curſe,</hi> Mal. 4. 6.</p>
            <p>Now may theſe Words be <hi>as Goads</hi> and <hi>as Nails: Goads</hi> to put us on to this <hi>duty; Nails</hi> to <hi>fix</hi> and <hi>faſten</hi> us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, Eccleſ. 12. 11.</p>
            <p>If any, when they have read this, with the following Tract, ſhall think meanly of it, or carp at the Author, as one that hath taken upon him a mean Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, thus to Write and Print a
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:51600:11"/> Book, chiefly to induce and direct Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, to make uſe of Books written by other Men; I only Anſwer, That ſo many able Pens have been already ſo variouſly employed in writing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications on thoſe Excellent Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſms of the Aſſembly, that theſe would give a <hi>Superſedeas</hi> to my Writing, were I ever ſo well qualified for it. I may, in this caſe, allude to that, <hi>For what can the man do, that cometh after the king? even that which hath been already done.</hi> Eccleſ. 2. 12. Or as it is in the Marginal reading, <hi>In thoſe things which have been already done.</hi> But, beſide, ſome are fitter to ſerve un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der others, than be Maſter Work-men. It may be enough for me, if I can follow the Reapers, and bind up what more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Labourers have laid ready to my Hand. I have what I aim at, if I can, by the Addition of this one little Wheel, give Motion to thoſe greater Ones, that have been wrought by abler Hands.</p>
            <p>The God of Heaven himſelf bleſs this to every Family, and Perſon, to whom it ſhall come.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Conſider what I have ſaid, and the Lord give you <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in all Things.</hi> Amen.</q>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:51600:12"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51600:12"/>
            <head>AN EARNEST CALL TO <hi>Family-Catechiſing,</hi> AND REFORMATION, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Introduction. The general Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod propoſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AMong the many deadly Symptoms of the Decays of Religion, and near Approach of Judgments, one of the greateſt is the ſo viſible Declenſions of Piety, and Increaſes of Sin and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not only in the open World, but in thoſe that would be counted Chriſtian Families It is a great Mercy to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51600:13"/> built up in Families, and no ſmall Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be the Head of one of thoſe little Common-wealths; but withall, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Truſt, and future Account is great. Every Perſon in the Family, is a Soul committed to the Care of ſuch as do, or ſhould govern. The Church, in her Firſt Infancy, for above Two thouſand Years, was nurſed in the Families of the Patriarchs, and then God's whole Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was uſually there celebrated: and tho' afterward, God inlarged the Borders of his Church, and then appointed ſome Solemn parts of his Worſhip, to be more publickly Adminiſtred; yet it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt unto Reaſon, back'd with undeniable Inſtances, That God never deſigned his People ſhould turn all Religion out of their Doors. In general, they are in their Families, to offer-up the Sacrifice of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Praiſe, to read the Holy Scriptures, ſing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. 20. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 59. 21. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 39. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 118. 15. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 30. <hi>Title. Pſalm</hi> 101.</note> Pſalms, and inſtruct their Houſholds in the Things of God, and walk before them in his Fear: And more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, they are to deal with reſpective Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, under their Charge, by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, Inſtruction, Encouragement, Reproof, Correction, as the Matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; and if, after all, they remain Sons
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51600:13"/> of <hi>Belial,</hi> will not be reformed themſelves, but endanger the corrupting of others; having duly ſought God for them, and with all long-ſuffering, waited to ſee, if God peradventure will give them Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, they are at laſt to exclude them the Family, whether they be Children, or Servants, which is a little Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: tho' upon their Repentance, and Reformation, they may be received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. But how ſad is it, that in moſt of the Families that call themſelves Chriſtian, there is little, yea nothing of this Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but, on the contrary, precious time ſpent on Cards and Dice; their Diſcourſes, not only vain and frothy, but ſtuff'd with fulſome and abominable Oaths, and Execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; a height of Vanity in their Attire, immoderate Expence in Furniture, mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Exceſs in Eating and Drinking, with a full purſuit of Eaſe and Pleaſure, or Worldly Profit; and all this cloakt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, at the moſt, with an empty Form of Godlineſs, as vain as the reſt: And if there be any one in the Family of a more ſerious Spirit and Deportment, and that cannot run with the reſt to the ſame Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of Riot, he or ſhe is but the May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game of the other: As if, to be truly Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious were the only Vice, to be Vitious the only Vertue; as if it were meritorious to be Vile, and the only way to eſcape Cenſure, were to deſerve it. What a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51600:14"/> Thing it were, if one could do any Thing toward the putting ſome ſtop to that mighty Torrent of Sin, and Wrath, that at once threaten us, now Deep calleth unto Deep, by an effectual promoting of Family-Reformation!</p>
               <p>But tho' I wiſh Families univerſally regulated, yet there is one ſpecial Duty I ſhall more particularly inſiſt upon, namely, Family-Catechiſing, which is ſuch a Duty, as being well managed, would influence us to many other.</p>
               <p>I ſhall briefly open the Nature of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing, and prove it to be a duty; direct Parents, and Governours of Families, as to the Performance of it; offer ſome Motives, for their ſo doing; give ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the governed Part of Families; lay down ſome Inducements to them, to ſubmit to thoſe Directions; and in the Cloſe, Anſwer thoſe Objections, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the governing, or governed Part of Families, may make againſt what I am propoſing. Of each in a diſtinct Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51600:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>What Catechiſing is. Publick Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing by the Minister, and private Catechiſing by the Heads and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of Families, proved a Duty by Scripture. A Catechiſm ought to contain a Form of ſound Words. The Catechiſms of the late Aſſembly recommended.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CAtechiſing in general, is any Inſtruction by Word of Mouth; more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly it is a plain and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar inſtructing of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> à <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſono, eſt vivâ voce inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ere. <hi>To inſtruct by Word of Mouth.</hi>
                  </note> in the Rudiments of any Doctrine: but yet moſt ſtrictly of all it is taken for teaching the Principles of Chriſtian Religion; and we have both the Word and Thing it ſelf in Scripture. This Catechiſing is either pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and as ſuch performed by a Miniſter of the Goſpel. Saith the Apoſtle, <hi>let him that is Taught or Catechiſed, in the Word, communicate unto him that Teacheth or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſeth in all good things,</hi> Gal. 6. 6. where we read both of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſt</hi> or him that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſeth, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumen,</hi> or the Perſon Catechiſed. In a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51600:15"/> place the ſame Apoſtle mentions <hi>Inſtructors of Children,</hi> as the Greek Word in its <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 15. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſtrictneſs ſignifies. And there were in the Primitive Churches Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſts, that is, Teachers, whoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Work it was to Catechiſe, and they had their Catechumens, thoſe that were inſtructed by them; and it might be to very good purpoſe, if we had ſuch now.</p>
               <p>But to deſcend from Publick to Private, or Family-Catechiſing, and Inſtruction, which we have both Scripture-Precept and Precedent for. We have, among other, theſe Scripture-Precepts and Commands for it: <hi>Theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thine heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy children, and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thy Houſe,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 6. 6, 7, 8, 9. So in another place, <hi>But teach them thy ſons, and thy ſons ſons,</hi> &amp;c. Deut. 4. 9, 10. Saith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78. 5, 6, 7. <hi>He eſtabliſhed a teſtimony in Jacob, and appointed a law in Iſrael, which he commanded our fathers, that they ſhould make them known to their Children,</hi> &amp;c. Saith <hi>Solomon, train up,</hi> or Catechiſe, <hi>a Child in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6. <hi>in the Margin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>way he ſhould go,</hi> &amp;c. Add to the reſt that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Fathers, provoke not your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to Wrath, but bring them up in the Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; Admonition of the Lord.</hi> Eph. 6. 4 I will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51600:15"/> now paſs from Scripture-Precepts to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-Precedents and Examples, whereby this Duty of Family-Catechiſing is further confirmed. <hi>Solomon</hi> writ his book of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, <hi>To give ſubtlety to the ſimple, to the young man knowledge and diſcretion,</hi> Prov. 1. 1, 4. And he calls upon his own Son, thus, <hi>My Son, hear the inſtructions of a father, and forſake not the law of thy Mother,</hi> ver. 8. He ſaith afterwards, <hi>A wiſe ſon heareth his father's inſtruction,</hi> Prov. 13. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which implieth, that a wiſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will give inſtruction to his Son. He concludes that book of wiſe Sayings with <hi>the words of King</hi> Lemuel, <hi>the prophecy that his mother taught him,</hi> Prov: 31. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which contains indeed moſt excellent Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techetical Inſtructions. <hi>Joſhua</hi> reſolved, <hi>that he and his houſe would ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſ. 24. 15. having likewiſe, no doubt, ſo inſtructed them, and intending to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo doing. Who can doubt but <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> had been thus Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed by his good <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5.</note> and <hi>Grand-Mother,</hi> whoſe <hi>faith</hi> he inherited? But a great and ſtanding Inſtance, is that of <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull, and, no doubt, to be imitated by all his Spiritual Children. Now of him God himſelf teſtifieth: <hi>I know him that he will command his children, and his houſhold after him; and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:51600:16"/> 
                  <hi>Judgment, that the Lord may bring upon Abraham that which he hath ſpoken of him,</hi> Gen. 18. 19. Thus you ſee we have both Scripture-Precepts and Precedents for the Warrant of this Duty of Family-Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing and Inſtruction: And what is there recorded, is for our admonition.</p>
               <p>Inſtruction ought indeed to be given occaſionally, yea, and all occaſions taken for it. But publick and Family-Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing cannot be methodically, and throughly managed, unleſs the chief heads of Chriſtian Doctrine be firſt digeſted in a Form of Sound Words according to the Scriptures. Now beſides many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Catechiſms ready provided to our hands, we have thoſe of that Reverend Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, which I recommend to you as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little, but withall great Body of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: and likewiſe becauſe divers holy and good Men have written very worthily thereon, whoſe books may aſſiſt your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding herein with more eaſe and profit both to your ſelves and Families.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:51600:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Directing Parents and Governours of Families, for the Catechiſing of their Families.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Now proceed to direct ſuch as are Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Children, and Governours of Families, as to a method of procedure. Wherein I include thoſe of the Female Sex, who have the greateſt Advantage of Form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children in their younger Years; and whoſe Buſineſs engageth them to be more conſtantly at home. <hi>If Queen</hi> Eſther <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a private faſt, her maidens ſhall faſt alſo,</hi> Eſther 4. 16. And no doubt, ſhe engaged them in more ordinary, as well as theſe extraordinary Duties of Religion. Mothers ſhould be Mothers in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> How the Royal <hi>Bathſheba</hi> did document her <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon;</hi> and honeſt and religious <hi>Lois</hi> and <hi>Eunice</hi> did inſtruct their <hi>Timothy</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-knowledge, I have already inſtanced. Good <hi>Monica</hi>'s Soul underwent ſtronger Travail-Pangs for the new Birth of her <hi>Auſtin,</hi> than her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy did for his firſt <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>Confeſſion.</hi>
                  </note> Birth. Can you bear the Thoughts of it, That thoſe whom you have born from the Womb, that have hung on your Breaſt, and been dand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51600:17"/> on your Knees, ſhould be Fire-brands in Hell to all Eternity; and not rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and endeavour they may be Heirs of Eternal Glory?</p>
               <p>Now to One and All of you, I ſay in this Caſe, as <hi>Jotham</hi> in another to the men of <hi>Shechem, Hearken unto me, that God may hearken unto you,</hi> Judg. 9. 7.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I deſire Parents of Children and Governours of Families to conſider with themſelves, what a great, neceſſary, and beneficial Duty, this of Catechiſing is. Humble your ſelves in ſecret before the Lord, for your ſo great, and long neglects of it. Beg of God, Courage for, and Conduct and Succeſs in it. Reſolve, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, that you will break through all Temptations and Oppoſitions, and ſet upon this Duty, and ſtudy to do it to the beſt advantage.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Having thus ſolemnly prepared your ſelves for this Work: In the next place, prepare your Families: Acquaint them, you are convinced, it is your Duty, to be concerned for the Souls committed to you; and that you look upon Catechiſing, as a proper Means for their Inſtruction and confirmation in thoſe great Truths, which they ought to believe, and Duties they ought to practiſe. Let them know, you expect their Compliance in a Matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God may be ſo much glorified, and they benefited. Put them upon ſolemn Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51600:17"/> for it; and if you have obſerved ſinful Miſcarriages in any, give them par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Admonitions. As <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid to his houſhold and all that were with him, <hi>Put away the ſtrange gods that are among you, and be ye clean; and let us ariſe and go up to Bethel, and I will make there an altar un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. 2, 3. So do you ſay unto your Family, when you are making your Houſe a <hi>Bethel, a Houſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. See that your Family get the Anſwers of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi>'s <hi>Catechiſm</hi> by memory, ſo as to be able to repeat them perfectly, and diſtinctly, without Book; which when they have done, ſo far as is neceſſary for your beginning, then ſet a-part ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient time, at leaſt once a Week; and, if any extraordinary Occaſion neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diverts you at that Seaſon, be ſure you take ſome other. And when you actually engage in this Holy Exerciſe, let not the Family be ſcatter'd here and there; nor ſome engage in the Service of the World, or be idly chatting, while others are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in the Service of God: but ſummon the whole Family together, and let them ſolemnly preſent themſelves, as before the Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As to the Actual Performance of the Duty it ſelf, I would direct you to a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod ſo eaſie, that thoſe of the meaneſt Capacities may comply with it. And (1.) Begin with Prayer to God for his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51600:18"/> Aſſiſtance and Bleſſing in this Work; for it is <hi>he muſt teach to profit,</hi> Iſa. 48. 17. and <hi>none teacheth like him,</hi> Job 36. 22. Pray that God would make it a Means of Enlightning your Minds, Confirming and Eſtabliſhing your Judgments, Convincing your Conſciences, Moving your Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Engaging your Hearts, of Converting you to God, and Building you up in Faith and Holineſs, and ſo of bringing you to eternal Happineſs and Salvation. Having thus prayed to God, (2.) Apply your ſelves to your Family, asking them ſome Queſtions in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi>'s <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> to which let them return the Anſwers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Book, audibly, diſtinctly, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. Two or Three Anſwers, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, are as many as you can well inſiſt on at one time. And ſince learning theſe, and repeating them only by rote, is of lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Signification, I do further adviſe you, (3.) To ask them By-Queſtions for the Proving, and Improving their Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in thoſe Truths; and for your own, and their Eaſe, in this Part of the Work, I do recommend to you Mr. <hi>Lye's Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Aſſembly</hi>'s <hi>Catechiſm,</hi> or that written by Mr. <hi>Joſeph Allein</hi> The former is more full, Mr. <hi>Lye</hi> writing his laſt of that nature, after the other; and having alſo a peculiar Talent for promoting this excellent Work. Toward the cloſe of which Book, there is a moſt Uſeful Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betical
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51600:18"/> Table, explaining the difficult Words and Terms throughout the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm:</hi> But the <hi>Latter</hi> ſome have choſen to uſe, as more familiar. In both theſe, you have Queſtions fitted to your Hand; ſo that you need only to read them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly and intelligibly, and the Matter is reduc'd to ſuch a Method, (eſpecially in Mr. <hi>Lye</hi>'s) that the Learner may return his Anſwers with a ſingle <hi>Yes,</hi> or <hi>No.</hi> (4.) When you have finiſhed this Part of your Work, I would have you, if time will permit (elſe at ſome other time) read Mr. <hi>Thomas Vincent's Explicatory Catechiſm,</hi> ſo far as concerns the Anſwers you have been upon. (5.) When you have done Catechiſing, ſing the whole, or ſome part of a Pſalm, ſuited, ſo near as you can, to that ſubject you have been upon: And upon Acquaintance with the Pſalms, it will hardly be poſſible for you to inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Two or Three Anſwers, but you may find ſome Pſalm very ſuitable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. This being devoutly performed, will yield unſpeakable, both Delight and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Then, (6.) Conclude all with Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God, for a Bleſſing on his own Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance. And if the time you pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be the Evening, you may in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding Prayer, commit your Selves and Families to God, for that Night, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to join Praiſes with your Prayers. All this, I conceive, may be performed in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51600:19"/> one Hours time, or within it, unleſs read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi>'s <hi>Explicatory Catechiſm,</hi> ſhould cauſe you to exceed. To prevent which, you may, as you ſee Occaſion, omit ſome part, or the whole of that, till ſome other Evening of the Week. (7.) You may alſo do well to ſignifie, That if any of them have Doubts and Objections, they ſhould, at convenient times, move them to you, which will put you upon further Study and Conſideration; and ſo in teaching them, you will learn your ſelves. If their Queſtions or Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions puzzle you, ſo that you cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them with due Satisfaction, apply your ſelves to your Miniſter, which will put him upon ſtudying the Caſe, and be a Mutual Advantage both to him and you. Yea, he will hereby, in ſome meaſure, know the Spiritual State, both of the Sheep and Lambs of his Flock. (8.) When you have throughly verſed your Selves, and Families in the ſhorter, you may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Larger Catechiſm</hi> of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi> And having firſt gone through the Catechiſms, without the Proofs, you may then put your Family upon learning thoſe, and particularly examine them, what Part of the Anſwer the Proof is brought to confirm, and what Part of the Proof confirms that Part of the Anſwer. This will not a little promote your knowledge of, and confirmation in the Truths of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51600:19"/> God. I have been more large on this Fourth Particular, becauſe it is directive to the Actual Performance of this Duty. Beſide the Books before-mention'd, Mr. <hi>Doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>little</hi>'s <hi>Scheme of the Aſſembly's Catechiſm,</hi> Printed in a ſingle Sheet, is worth every Families having. (5.) Labour to be well grounded your ſelves, and confirm thoſe under your Charge, in the great Articles of Chriſtian Faith; as the Being of God, the Oneneſs of his Eſſence; the Trinity of Perſons, or Subſiſtences; the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, his Perſon, his Natures, Divine and Humane; his Offices, Kingly, Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Prophetick; his Sufferings, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Aſcenſion, Interceſſion, ſitting at God's Right Hand; his future Judging the World, with all other his Glorious Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; the abſolute Neceſſity of Faith in him, and intire reliance on his Merits, as the only Matter of our Righteouſneſs, for Juſtification; that true Juſtifying Faith works by Love, and without Works, Faith is Dead. The total Impotence of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, as to all Spiritual Operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Abſolute Neceſſity of the Energy of the Spirit of God; yet that it is our Duty to be converſant with the Means; That the Holy Scriptures are a ſufficient Rule for Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline and Converſation. Let theſe, and the like Principles, be engraven on your Hearts, that you may be nouriſhed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51600:20"/> 
                  <hi>up in the words of faith and of good Doctrine, whereunto you have attained,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 6.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Take great care, that God's Sabbaths be ſtrictly obſerved, and induſtriouſly employed by your Selves and Families. As the Miſimproving of this day is one great in let to all prophaneneſs, ſo the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Improvement of it, will much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance all true Piety. The Sabbath ſhould have its Double of Offerings. You will thrive in Spirituals all the Week, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Spiritual Induſtry that day. The Fourth Command is primarily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to Parents and Governours of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, who are reſponſible for themſelves, and thoſe under them.</p>
               <p n="7">7. See to it, that as you profeſs your ſelves a Chriſtian Family, ſo you maintain Univerſal Holineſs of Converſation. Let no duty be omitted, or Sin committed with thy connivance. Look ſtrictly to it, that all relative Duty be duely diſcharged; in which much of your Religion conſiſts, and on which the Credit of Religion and our own Comfort, very much depends. Make a compaſſionate, but faithfull uſe of that Authority which God has committed to thee; and withall, ſee to it, that thou <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have thy ſelf wiſely in a perfect way, and walk within thy houſe with a perfect heart, ſetting no wicked thing before thee,</hi> Pſal. 101. 2, 3. Elſe thy Endeavours for the Good of others, are like to be both heartleſs, and fruitleſs.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:51600:20"/>
               <p n="8"> 8. This one thing I would add, which I would have by no means forgotten, That you do not confine your ſelves only to thoſe of your own Family, but invite, and encourage any other Families (that have not, or cannot have thoſe Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages) to come in among you, which will be a great piece of Soul-charity. This I now mention, is not invading the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Office or Work, any more than it is to admit the Members of ſome poor, prayerleſs Family to partake of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily-Devotions. Yea, this being well regulated may be made greatly ſubſervient to more publick Catechiſing performed by the Miniſter, and I have experimentally found it ſo.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Let me ſuperadd this. If at any time you ſlip into Neglects of, or Remiſneſs in your Family-Duties (and our deceitfull Hearts, a ſubtle Devil, &amp; an inſnaring world will be apt to give us too many Avocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) ſee that you carefully re-aſſume your Duty again, and endeavour to recover your Zeal and Warmth therein. And in caſe there be any extraordinary cauſe, either from Omiſſions of Duty, or Commiſſions of Sin, ſolemnly humble your ſelves <hi>as a family with faſting and prayer,</hi> Zech. 12. 12, 13, 14. To implore God's Pardon and Favour; and let this be followed with as ſolemn Reformation.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:51600:21"/>
               <p>Thus I have, according to the meaſure of my Ability, given you Directions for the profitable managing this great Duty of <hi>Family-Catechiſing,</hi> and Reformation. Now the Lord himſelf direct you, both to, and in the Performance hereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Some Motives offered to Family-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, in behalf of Family-Catechiſing.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF it can be needfull, to add Motives for the further inforcing that Advice I have given, I would offer ſuch as theſe; which I ſhall, for brevity ſake, deliver more promiſcuouſly, and not ſtand to draw out under particular Heads. <hi>Catechiſing</hi> is a Duty, yea an advantagious Duty; and, being well managed, may meet with thoſe, who reap little or no benefit by Sermons, or continued Diſcourſes: For this is more ſuited to the Capacities of youth; it doth more neceſſitate their Attention, and put them upon the Exerciſe both of Memory, and Judgment. It is a proper Means of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting, and increaſing Knowledge, and that not only in regard of its familiar Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion; but alſo, as in a little compaſs, it takes in the whole Body, and Syſtem of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51600:21"/> Divinity: and Divine knowledge is of all moſt excellent. It further tends to ſettle and confirm the Judgment in the great Truths to be believed, and Duties to be practiſed. Many let go Truth, becauſe they never had faſt hold of it. <hi>Catechiſing</hi> is a great means of Prevention of Apoſtaſy; and had we retained more of the former, we had ſeen leſs of the latter. It may alſo be a happy means of preventing many, yea and great Sins, or ſpeedy convincing the Conſcience where Sin hath prevailed. How many from mere Ignorance of the Extent of God's Commands, have not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen into great Sins, but continued in them without repentance, to whom good Inſtruction might have been a Means of Prevention, or Recovery. This may be a Means of working and promoting Faith, and Holineſs of Heart, and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; yea all Good here and hereafter. By Catechiſing thoſe under your charge, you may mend your own Head and Heart. <hi>Family-Catechiſing</hi> will be mainly ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to that great Duty of <hi>Publick Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing:</hi> And who knows, but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the one and the other, the Enemy, Sin, may be be-ſet before and behind, and fall in battel. Theſe two may be like the former and latter rain promoting all Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fruitfulneſs. Sure, if as children are ſolemnly dedicated to God in Baptiſm; ſo parents did conſcienciouſly endeavour to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51600:22"/> bring them up for God, and care were further taken by publick Catechiſing and Inſtructions to fit them for, and tranſmit them to a compleat ſtate of Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: Churches would (by the bleſſing of God) be more plentifully ſtockt from Chriſtian Families, beſide the children of the Stranger that might be joined to the Lord.</p>
               <p>By working on the Young Ones of the preſent Age, an Earneſt may be laid for the good of ſucceeding Generations: Yea a Seed of your own may be raiſed up to praiſe the Lord, and bear up his Name in the World. Thus may your own <hi>Gardens flouriſh,</hi> the <hi>tender grapes appear, and your Pomgranats bud forth,</hi> Song 7. 12. <hi>Your Sons</hi> (thus manured) <hi>may be as plants growing up in their youth, and your daughters (thus ſquared) may be as corner-ſtones poliſhed after the Similitude of a palace,</hi> Pſal. 144. 12. And you may, at the laſt day, give up your account with joy; and ſay, <hi>Here am I, Lord, and the children that thou haſt given me,</hi> and then ſhall you and they be for <hi>ever together with the Lord:</hi> be <hi>pillars</hi> in the heavenly Temple, and never be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved thence. Thus have I finiſhed what I intend for the Governing part of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: I ſhall now addreſs my ſelf to the Governed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:51600:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Advice to the Governed part of Families.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE former part more-eſpecially relates unto Parents of Children, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Families. It may, I conceive, be needful to ſubjoyn ſome particular Advice to Children and Servants; or any other, who may be the governed part of Families. For if Means of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be uſed by Family-Governours; yet if it have not a due influence upon the Family under their Charge, it doth not reach its End, but is like Water ſpilt upon the Ground. And I am the rather induced to apply my ſelf particularly unto you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Governed is uſually the moſt numerous part of the Family: And tho' you are at preſent, in regard of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Circumſtances, the inferiour part of it; yet you have as precious Souls as your Parent, and Governours. God is equally concerned for you, and has commanded Miniſters to feed his <hi>Lambs,</hi> as well as <hi>Sheep,</hi> Joh. 21. 15, 16, 17. And we do profeſs our Selves the Servants of all; yea, and your ſelves have as much reaſon to be concerned for your own Souls, as your Parents and Governours have for theirs.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51600:23"/> In this ſence, our Salvation is <hi>common Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> Jude, <hi>v.</hi> 3. and there is no diſtinction of <hi>bond</hi> or <hi>free,</hi> Gal. 3. 28. Yea, if God lengthen out your Days, (and Obedience is the way to long Life,) you that are now Children and Servants, may become Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Children, and have Servants under you, being built up in Families of your own. Now the better you are at preſent in your private Station, the better you may be when advanced to a more publick Capacity: For to Obey well, is the way to Govern well. So that ſetting of you right for the preſent, may be a Means of regulating your Families for the future; and thoſe who ſhall receive holy Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from you, may afterward convey the ſame to their Families: And who knows, but as there ſhall ever be a holy Seed, raiſed up to praiſe and ſerve the Lord; ſo there may be a Succeſſion of Religion in thoſe that deſcend from you, till the coming of Chriſt to Judgment. It is obſervable, That though God calls home to himſelf ſome who were far off; and he will yet more eminently do ſo, <hi>when all the ends of the earth ſhall remember and turn to the Lord, and all the kindreds of the nations ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip before him,</hi> Pſal. 22. 27. Yet, Religion hath been much propagated through the Loins of the Faithful. And it hath been obſerved, That when Grace gets into a Family, ordinarily it doth not ſoon take
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51600:23"/> its leave of it: But though there may be ſome ſad Interruptions, yet it appears ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times again in Grand-Children, or Great-Grand-Children; and if not in the direct Line, yet Collaterally; as the Rivers of Water run thorough the Valleys, though not in a direct Courſe, but with many Windings and Turnings, and various Branchings; ſo that we are many times ready to be at a loſs in following them. Of this the Scripture doth, and our own Obſervation may, furniſh us with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
               <p>Now may I not begin my Addreſs to you, as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> one of his Sermons, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad vos, Juvenes, mibi ſermo; flos aetatis periculum mentis.</hi> Aug. de Temp.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">O, Young Ones, my Speech is to you who are in the flower of your Age, but peril and danger of Mind.</q> Or with very little Variation, as St. <hi>John,</hi> that boſome Diſciple of our Lord, <hi>I have written unto you, fathers, that you may know him that is from the beginning. I now write unto you, little children, that you may know the father. I write unto you, young men, that you may be ſtrong, and overcome the wicked one, and that the word of God may abide in you,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 12, 13, 14. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Come ye children, hearken unto me, I will teach you the fear of the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 34. 11. I ſhall give you the ſum of my Advice, in the following Particulars.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51600:24"/>
               <p n="1"> (1.) Conſider ſeriouſly, what kind of Creatures God hath made you, and learn to ſet a due value upon your own beings. The very Frame of thy Body, which is <hi>wonderfully and fearfully made, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly wrought,</hi> Pſal. 139. 14, 15. ſpeaks ſomething extraordinary. But then thy Soul is Heaven-born, a Spiritual and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Being, capable of the Knowledge and Enjoyment of God himſelf; and by what Bonds and Tyes this Material Body and Immaterial Soul are united and linked together, thou do'ſt not know. So that thine own Being is above thy Conception. St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Confeſ.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">wonders that Men admire other things, and leave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unadmired.</q> Conſider, thou art not a lifeleſs Rock or Stone, a ſenſeleſs Plant or Tree, an irrational brute Beaſt; but a Creature endowed with a rational and immortal Soul, capable of knowing and enjoying God here and hereafter: Yea, thy mortal Body ſhall, at the laſt day, be raiſed to an Immortal State. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, thou art a Creature made for Eternity.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Seriouſly lay to heart your State of Sin and Miſery: How you are tainted with <hi>Adam</hi>'s firſt Tranſgreſſion. The Scriptures of Truth acquaint us, That <hi>in him all ſinned, and therefore death came upon all men,</hi> Rom. 5. 12. And <hi>in Adam all</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51600:24"/> 
                  <hi>died.</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 22. Conſider further how your whole Nature, Soul and Body, every Faculty of the one, and Member of the other is vitiated, and defiled with the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of Sin. Thou haſt within, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee a compleat Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Sin and Death, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 24.</note> with all its Members. Even the youngeſt Children have old <hi>Adam</hi> in them. Infants themſelves are not inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. Thou haſt that Corruption within thee, which is ſufficient to betray thee to the greateſt Sins, and expoſe thee to the greateſt Sufferings. Yea, thou art guilty of manifold actual Sins of Omiſſion, and Commiſſion, and theſe cloathed with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Aggravations. O! Conſider how thy excellent Being is debaſed by Sin, and how thou haſt plunged thy ſelf into un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, yea unconceivable Miſery.</p>
               <p n="3">(3) See that thou be regenerate and born again, without which, thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enter into the Kingdom of God. Thou art by Nature <hi>a child of Wrath,</hi> and Heir of Hell. Thy Nature muſt be changed by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 3. 3. 5.</note> Grace, before thou canſt be a Child of God, and Heir of Heaven. And this know, and remember, that the New Birth is of the whole Man, as the Natural is, if it be a living Birth. Remember your ſolemn Dedication to God in Baptiſm obligeth you to ſecure
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51600:25"/> your Regeneration, improve it therefore accordingly. If taken out of the World by Death, before thou art taken out of the World by Grace; it had been good for thee thou hadſt never been born; for thou art undone to Eternity. Woe to thee, if thou dieſt before thou art alive to God: for on ſuch the ſecond Death ſhall have Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and they ſhall be kill'd with Death.</p>
               <p n="4">(4.) Have, and maintain an inward Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and Eſteem of your Parents, Maſters, and Governours: Yea, tho' they be not ſo great, or rich, or wiſe, or obliging, as ſome others. Eſteem them as thoſe ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you in the Lord, and as obeying the Lord in ſo doing. <q rend="inline">I have heard of a Wife who ſaid ſhe could be Obedient to her Husband, but he was ſuch a one as did not deſerve it.</q> It was reply'd, <q rend="inline">But the Command of God is worthy to be obey'd, and ſhew your Obedience unto that.</q> So in this Caſe, The Yoke will gall if it be not lined with Love: but Love will cover a multitude of Faults. Beſide the Sin of Undutifulneſs, we profit little by thoſe whom we do not much affect.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Study the Duties of your particular Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ</hi> 4. 11. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and Relations, and conſcientiouſly practiſe them. Many ſtudy other Duties, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>their own. They ſpy a Mote in anothers eye, and cannot ſee a beam in their own.</hi> Do
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51600:25"/> you eſpecially ſtudy and perform your own Duties. Let your words, looks, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, actions, be ſuch towards Parents and Superiours as they ought to be. Let their Cautions reſtrain you from all Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their Counſels ſet you upon the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of what is Duty. Yea, tho Parents and Maſters do not perform their Duty to thee, yet thou muſt perform thine both to God, and them. <hi>You muſt be ſubject with all fear, not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 18. their Sin can be no Diſpenſation or Abſolution to thee.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In every Employment aim principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the Glory of God. If thou learneſt, learn for God: if thou workeſt, work for God. In the choice of a Calling, be for that in which thou mayeſt moſt Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God. Yea, let thy very Recreations be ſuch and ſo timed, as may ſubſerve this great end. If thou unbendeſt the Bow, and oyleſt the Wheels, let it be, to fit for Service.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Let thy whole ſelf be found in all thoſe religious Duties which God requires. You are to read, meditate, and pray in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. Saith our Saviour, <hi>Thou when thou prayeſt, enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut the door, pray to thy father which is in ſecret,</hi> Mat. 6. 6. Now remember to bow thy Heart, as well as Knees. <hi>Who is this that engageth his heart to approach unto</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:51600:26"/> 
                  <hi>me, ſaith the Lord?</hi> Jer. 30. 21. Offer not the Sacrifice of fools without an Heart. God will not accept of an heartleſs Sacrifice, <hi>He is a Spirit, and will be worſhiped in Spirit, as well as in truth,</hi> Joh. 4. 24. And for Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Worſhip, while the Word of God is reading, or Prayer made, let not thine Ear be liſtning, or Eye wandring after other things, nor thy Heart be with the fools in the fartheſt parts of the Earth. Let not the Lord be nigh in thy Mouth, and far from thy Reins, but ſet and keep thy heart to the duty. When Pſalms are ſinging, make not thy ſelf a Mute, ſince God hath not made thee ſo. Let not a dumb Devil poſſeſs thee, but tune thy Heart and thy Voice unto God's praiſes. So when preſent at God's Publick Worſhip, let not thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part be abſent.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Submit willingly and conſcienciouſly to Family-Catechiſing and Inſtruction. When Parents and Governours of Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies have overcome their own inward Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragments, let them not meet with new Conflicts and Diſcouragements from thee. Be ready to learn, ſubmit to Examination, ſtudy the Sence and Meaning of what you learn, ask queſtions, for your farther In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, of theſe Elders, or more expert than your ſelves: Enquire of your Parents or Governours, or Miniſters, or any other able to inſtruct you. It is obſerved, That
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51600:26"/> thoſe who are much in moving pertinent Queſtions, make the beſt Scholars.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Carefully avoid all Sin, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch againſt thoſe Sins that you may be moſt in danger of. Saith the Apoſtle, <hi>Flee youthful luſts,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 22. Among theſe let me caution you, 1. Againſt Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Dare not to uſe it, either to cover a Fault, or gain a ſeeming Advantage. The Lyer is not true to himſelf: his Heart and his Tongue are diſtorted one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He deceives his Neighbour, directly oppoſeth the glorious Attribute of God's Truth, makes a deep Wound upon his own Conſcience, and, without repentance, will meet with his Reward in Hell. 2. Dread Swearing, Curſing, taking the Name of God in vain, and all evil ſpeaking: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your Tongues are not your own, but God is Lord over you and them. Let that Scripture be engraven on your Heart, <hi>But I ſay unto you, That every idle word that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof in the day of Judgment: for by thy words thou ſhalt be juſtified, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned,</hi> Mat. 12. 36, 37. 3. Avoid all Pride in Heart, Life and Attire. Be cloathed with Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 5. 4. Shun idleneſs How canſt thou have nothing to do, who haſt a God to ſerve, and a Soul to ſave? When idle, thou tempteſt the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51600:27"/> Tempter; and if thou findeſt nothing to do, he will find Employment for thee. 5. Keep thy ſelf free from Injuſtice and Defrauding. It is a great ſin; will make a great clamor, when Conſcience is awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and to make reſtitution, tho a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, is a very hard Duty; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore avoid the occaſion. <hi>The unrighteous ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 9. Let no ſin of this nature ſeem little to thee. St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> was brought to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, for robbing his neighbour's Pear-Tree; <note place="margin">Aug. Confeſſion.</note> Which ſin he greatly aggravates, as alſo his Couſenage in youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sports and Recreations. Take heed thou indulgeſt not thy ſelf in thoſe Tricks of Youth, which will afterward prove Sins of Youth, either here in the Day of Conſcience; or hereafter, at the Barr of God. 6. Take heed of the Sin of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, even to a laſcivious Look; yea, Thought; and be not by Speech, Garb, or Geſture, an Occaſion of Temptation to any. We muſt not only avoid the Snare our ſelves, but be carefull we do not ſpread Nets for others. 7. Be carefull thou doſt not drown thy ſoul in a Life of Pleaſure, Voluptuouſneſs and Exceſs. Be not of thoſe who are <hi>Lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God.</hi> 2. Tim. 3. 4. 8. Take heed of Worldlineſs. It is a ſin prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Youth, increaſeth with Age, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51600:27"/> will at laſt <hi>drown the Soul in perdition,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 9. 10. 9. Beware of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Obſtinacy, and Incorrigibleneſs. This remember; If thy Spirit get above the reach of Parents, and Superiours; yet thou art not out of God's reach, who will take the work into his own hand, and will certainly meet with thee to thy grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter trouble here, or eternal ſorrow hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In many places of the World, at this very day, God is fatning the ground with the Blood and Carcaſſes of children of Diſobedience. The Lord has ſaid, That <hi>the ſons of Belial ſhall be all of them as thorns thruſt away, becauſe they cannot be taken with hands; but the man that ſhall touch them muſt be fenced with Iron, and the ſtaff of a ſpear, and they ſhall be utterly burnt with Fire in the ſame place,</hi> 2. Sam. 23. 6, 7. 10. As you would avoid all other Sins, avoid evil Company. <hi>He that walketh with the wiſe, ſhall be more wiſe; but a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of fools, ſhall be deſtroyed,</hi> Prov. 13. 20.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Finally from an inward Principle of Religious Fear of God, practiſe uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, as becometh ſuch an one as is a Chriſtian indeed. Let Religion run thro your whole Converſation. Be that in your Bed, in your Cloſet, in the Family; in the World, that your Holy Profeſſion obligeth you to be. <hi>Whatever you do in word or deed, do all in the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> Col. 3. 17. Walk always, as under the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51600:28"/> Eye of God, and with ſerious Thoughtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Death, Judgment, and Eternity.</p>
               <p>Thus I have finiſhed my Advice to you who are the Governed Part of Families.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Some Motives to the Govern'd Part of Families, to ſubmit to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections preſcribed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Will ſubjoin a few Motives to induce the governed Part of Families to receive, and practiſe the Inſtructions I have given you, and particularly as to ſubmitting to Family-Catechiſing and Inſtruction.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Conſider how ignorant and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute you are by Nature of all true ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Good; how prone and inclined unto all Evil: <hi>Vain man would be wiſe, but he is born like the wild Aſſe Colt.</hi> Job 11. 12. Now the Aſs is a dull blockiſh Creature the wild Aſs an untractable Creature; and ſuch is Man by Nature.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Conſider it will be your great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and true Comfort, to hearken to Good Counſel and receive good Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that betimes: ſaith the Lord, <hi>Since thou haſt been precious in my ſight, thou haſt been honourable,</hi> Iſa. 43. 4. This
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51600:28"/> made <hi>Jabez more honourable than his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4. 9, 10. <hi>Wiſdoms ways are ways of pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are peace,</hi> Prov. 3. 17. All that ever walked in them, have found them ſo. They are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Strangers to them that ſuggeſt the contrary.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) Conſider how much Evil both of Sin and Puniſhment, thou mayeſt prevent, by a ſpeedy attending to wholſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and Inſtruction. Look upon thy whole Life, as a time of Temptation; yea, and the further thou engageſt in the World, the more thou ſhalt find the Temptations of it. Even Infancy hath its Temptations, but Childhood more than Infancy; Youth more than Childhood. There are ſuch filthy Luſts of the Fleſh, as make even a Child of God cry out, <hi>O wretched man that I am! Rom.</hi> 7. 24. And ſuch would be glad of Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, even by Death. Yea, it is a great Teſtimony of the truth of Grace, when we can deſirouſly ſubmit to Death, which even pure Nature is averſe unto, rather than be infeſted with Temptations unto thoſe Sins which corrupt Nature is moſt pleaſed with. And it is a further Teſtimony of the Grace of God in us, when yet we ſit patient and ſubmiſſive, though uneaſie, under this greateſt of Burthens, till God ſhall, in his own time and way, give us a fair diſcharge from our ſervice. But if theſe Temptations ſhould prevail, and you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51600:29"/> ſhould be induced <hi>to make proviſion for the fleſh, to ſatisfie the luſts thereof,</hi> Rom. 13. 14. what Wounds do you give to your own Souls? Great alſo are our Temptations, when we come to Man's Eſtate; for then ordinarily we engage more deeply in the World, a moſt dangerous Enemy. It was ſmartly, and as truly ſaid by one, <q rend="inline">The <hi>Devil</hi> of <hi>Buſineſs</hi> hurries more Souls to Hell, than all the Devils in Hell beſides.</q> At this age it is, that Perſons uſually enter on the Conjugal Relation, which ſo much influenceth the reſidue of our Lives; yea, and Poſterity after us: And if you ſhould arrive at Old Age, which few do; yet that, of all, is moſt unteachcable. As to Evil of Puniſhment, it is conſequent to that of Sin: Yea, God ſometimes, even where he forgives the Sin, and exempts from Hell, yet will not remit or abate the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Chaſtiſement here. Saith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, <hi>Thou anſwered'ſt them, O God! Thou waſt a God that forgaveſt them, though thou tookeſt vengeance upon their inventions,</hi> Pſal. 99. 8. <hi>God may viſit our tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions with the rod, and our iniquities with ſtripes, though he do not utterly take his loving-kindneſs away,</hi> Pſal. 89. 32, 33. At leaſt, Sin will coſt us a dear-bought Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. Now, how much of this Evil of Sin and Suffering may be happily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, by early attending to good Counſel and Inſtruction?</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51600:29"/>
               <p n="4"> (4.) Conſider the Shortneſs, and withal, Uncertainty of Time; and the vaſt Extent (if I may ſo ſpeak) and Concernment of Eternity. Thy Time will ſoon be at an end, how ſoon thou knoweſt not, and thou muſt take that amazing ſtep into an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which has no end.</p>
               <p n="5">(5.) Conſider, None ever complained they were brought to Acquaintance with God too early, but many have repented it was ſo late. Said <hi>Auſtin,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">I have loved thee late, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sero te amavi, veritas, tam anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua &amp; tam nova.</hi> Ang.</note> O thou Truth! ſo Ancient, and yet ſo New.</q> By which, I ſuppoſe, he meant, ſo Ancient in it ſelf, as being Eternal; and yet ſo New, that is, newly diſcovered unto him. Who was ever brought ſo early to God, but he wiſh'd it were yet earlier, if earlier it could be. I am ſure, in this, of the concurrent Teſtimony of all the Saints that are, or have been, or ever will be upon Earth: though, in this caſe, <hi>late</hi> is better than <hi>never;</hi> yet <hi>early</hi> is better than <hi>late.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">(6.) Conſider, As the Lord will be very gracious and indulgent toward you, if you hear Inſtructions that you may live; ſo he will be equally ſevere, if you reject his Counſel, and chuſe Death. God was highly pleaſed with his Sacrifice of Lambs, and his Offerings of Firſt-fruits: When the Ears were yet green, his Soul deſires the firſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51600:30"/> ripe Fruits. When any do early attend the Calls of God, He <hi>remembers the kindneſs of their youth, the love of their eſpouſals,</hi> Jer. 2. 2. <hi>The Shepherd of Iſrael, even the great Shepherd of the ſheep, gathers his lambs in his arms, and lays them in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> Iſa. 40. 11. But <hi>if you caſt his fear behind your backs, and walk contrary unto him, he will walk contrary unto you,</hi> Lev. 26. 23, 24. The <hi>Lamb of God</hi> is likewiſe the <hi>Lion</hi> of the <hi>Tribe of Judah,</hi> and will rend and <hi>tear,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> ſhall <hi>deliver</hi> out of his Hand, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 22. He hath his <hi>Iron Rod,</hi> as well as his <hi>Golden Scepter;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Kiſs the Son, leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way,</hi> Pſal. 2. 12.</p>
               <p>Thus I have been ſuggeſting Motives, the Lord himſelf move you by them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Objections Anſwered.</hi> The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>I Shall now apply my ſelf to Anſwer thoſe <hi>Objections,</hi> that either the Governors or Governed in Families, or both of them, may be apt to raiſe againſt the neceſſary and important Duty I have been urging. Yet thus much I muſt firſt premiſe in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51600:30"/> That there can, in this caſe, no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections be made, but ſuch as ſavour very ſtrongly of Weakneſs, Sloth, Earthlineſs, Impiety and Obſtinacy. But ſuch as they are, I ſhall give them a Hearing, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Anſwer them, that this Iniquity may for ever ſtop its mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Some weak Perſons may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt Catechiſing, as a <hi>Dead, Flat, Formal Thing, not ſuiting the Spirituality of the Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, (1.) Solemn Catechiſing, or Inſtructing Perſons in the chief Heads of Chriſtian Doctrine, is a Duty of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as neceſſarily requires a methodical Collection of thoſe fundamental Truths that lye ſcattered throughout the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. The Apoſtle mentions a <hi>Form of Doctrine delivered,</hi> Rom. 6. 17. And we are preſented with ſome of the fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Principles of the Doctrine of Christ,</hi> Heb. 6. 1. under certain Heads, methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and regularly diſpoſed. And <hi>Timothy</hi> is commanded, to <hi>hold faſt the form of ſound words, which</hi> he had received of <hi>Paul, in faith and love that is in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13.</p>
               <p>(2.) Whether, or how far Forms of Prayer are lawful, is nothing to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe to enquire: But this let me ſay, There is a manifeſt difference between Forms of Prayer, and thoſe impoſed; and Forms for Catechiſing, either compoſed or choſen, as adapted and fitted to that Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51600:31"/> which neceſſarily requires ſuch a Form.</p>
               <p>(3.) I plead, as much as you, againſt Formality in this, or any other Chriſtian Duty: yea, I exhort you to be Spiritual herein. We may be in danger of Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, without the Uſe of Forms; and we may, in ſome caſes, make uſe of Forms, and yet not be formal.</p>
               <p>(4.) Many Chriſtians that have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced high Communion with God, have been very Spiritual in theſe Exerciſes, and found their Spirituality promoted thereby.</p>
               <p>(5.) The great decay of Spirituality, has been more evident in the Chriſtian World, ſince the neglect of Catechiſing, than it was when this Ordinance has been more frequented. For the evincing of this, I deſire you to compare the good old Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan days with ours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>May ſome ſay, <hi>We ſcruple at this way of teaching, by</hi> Queſtion <hi>and</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: <hi>Where have we any Precept or Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for this, in the Word of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, (1.) God, in his Word, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Catechiſing and Inſtruction of Youth, we muſt perform it in that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod that may beſt conduce to the attaining the End.</p>
               <p>(2.) The Method of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer</hi> is a natural way of familiar, inſtructive Diſcourſe; and the very Light of Nature has directed the Heathen themſelves to the Uſe of it as <hi>Plato,</hi> and Others.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51600:31"/>
               <p>(3.) We have plentiful Scripture-Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God's diſcourſing with Men, and Men one with another by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer,</hi> in order to Information and Inſtruction. The book of <hi>Job</hi> furniſheth us with abundant examples, beſide many other in the <hi>New,</hi> as well as <hi>Old Teſtament:</hi> even our Lord Chriſt taught both Privately and Publickly, by way of <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(4.) Though I recommend this as a moſt proper, yet I do not aſſert it the only Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod for Familiar-Inſtruction, and my Reader has his liberty to uſe any other which he finds really conducing to this great End, as well as this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Some Parent or Governour of a Family may object, <hi>You put us upon a Task extreme difficult, and next to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: We are not Miniſters, nor can we Catechiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, (1.) I have proved it to be your Duty; and therefore you muſt not plead Difficulty. You are not to ſtand and diſpute, but go and obey.</p>
               <p>(2.) Being Duty, if it were a thouſand times more difficult than it is, God can, and, if the fault be not thy own, he will inable thee to perform it ſo, as ſhall be acceptable to him, and profitable to thy ſelf and others. Therefore Pray the more, but Practiſe never the leſs.</p>
               <p>(3.) According to the Method I have propoſed, the thing is not only poſſible,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51600:32"/> but may very eaſily be done. I adviſe you to begin and end with Prayer: and I hope you are come ſo far already, as to pray in your Families; Elſe you and they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that fearfull imprecatione, <hi>Pour out thy fury upon the heathen that know thee not, and upon the families that call not on thy name,</hi> Jer. 10. 25. For the Queſtions and Anſwers, you have them in the <hi>Aſſembly's Catechiſm;</hi> Mr. <hi>Allein</hi>'s, or Mr. <hi>Lye</hi>'s Book is ſufficient for the further Queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary part; and Mr. <hi>Vincent</hi>'s, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Expoſition. One that can but read, may do all this. And then canſt thou not read a Pſalm, fitted to be Sung, and ſome one in the Family ſet a tune to it? Set but thy heart toward the Work, and it will be eaſily done: be Spirituall in it, and it will be well done. But alas many Families plead themſelves off from the Duty of Singing Pſalms, becauſe there is not one among them can ſet a Pſalm-Tune, and but few that can follow it. To this I will only ſay, Can you not hear your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours children or ſervants ſing Ballads? Yea, do not ſome in your own Families (I ſpeak it to your ſhame) Sing vain and idle Songs? why cannot you as well learn Pſalm-Tunes, and Sing the Songs of <hi>Zion?</hi> Sure either you can ſing, or may learn. You have accompliſht as difficult Tasks in other kinds. Charge this on your ſelves as a Duty, and ſee what may be done.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51600:32"/> Look upon this as the higheſt Uſe and Employment your Tongues are given you for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>Some may object, <hi>Alas, we would be willing, yea, glad to be Catechiſed, but we are ſure the Heads of the Family that we are in will never be brought to perform this Duty, and ſo we are excus'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, (1.) The Governours of your Family ought to do it. Our Lord Chriſt has left no particular exception for them, and they muſt anſwer it to him if they do not perform it.</p>
               <p>(2.) Judge not uncharitably, before you have made trial. Dare you bear Falſe-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt, yea and judge your Superiour without hearing? Uſe all Endeavours to perſwade him. Let the Wife of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the Children of his Body, beg at him to take pity on his own, and their Souls. Let Friends, Sojourners and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, in all becoming ways, try to move him. One of our Lords Diſciples <hi>came to him to teach them to pray as John taught his diſciples, and our Lord immediately taught them.</hi> Luke 11. 1. So if you, with humility, ſay, Sir, other Maſters inſtruct their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, we beg you would likewiſe inſtruct us: it may be hoped he will do it. Nay may it not be ſaid, as was to <hi>Moſes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Aaron, Behold he cometh forth to meet thee, and when he ſeeth thee, he will be glad in his heart,</hi> Exod. 4. 14.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:51600:33"/>
               <p>(3) If the Maſter of the Family will by no means be prevailed with, (which I am hardly willing to ſuppoſe,) yet obtain, at leaſt, that another may do it for him. As the Wife, who is to be a help meet for him; or ſome Servant, or ſome one of the elder Children, <hi>The Jabez of the family that is more honourable than his brethren,</hi> 1 Chron. 4. 9, 10. Or call in the help of ſome charitable neighbour.</p>
               <p>(4) If you can by no means enjoy this beneficial Ordinance in your own Family, put in and joyn with ſome other. Beg this Bread abroad, rather than Starve at home.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Some may object, <hi>We are a buſy hurrying Family, and cannot ſpare time for it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, (1.) Your time is God's, and you ought not to rob him of his due.</p>
               <p>(2.) This great buſineſs, according to the Method I have propoſed, will take up very little time: it may be one hour in a week, which is but one hour of One Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sixty Eight.</p>
               <p>(3.) This will be no Loſs, but Gain of Time. God's Bleſſing will more than make it up. This Whet will be no Lett.</p>
               <p>(4.) For Shame, count not that Loſs of Time, which may be Gain for Eternity. Did ever any on a Death-bed, and when entring on Eternity, call that loſt Time which they ſpent in the Service of God and their Souls? Many then have called that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51600:33"/> time they have ſpent on the World ſo.</p>
               <p>(5.) Is not as much time actually miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpent by the Maſter of the Family at the Coffee-Houſe, and otherwiſe, and by the Family at home, as ought and might be employed in performing this, and other Family-Duties; Yea, of all the moſt ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time for theſe things, the Evening. Do you thus ſquander time away, and yet object the want of it?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Some Governour (or that ſhould be Governour) of a Family, may ſay, <hi>Do you put me upon Catechiſing? Alas, my Family will never bear it, nor endure me, if I ſhould attempt it. My Children are children of Belial. My Servants as ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernable and untractable, as the boiſtrous</hi> Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan, <hi>of whom it is ſaid, in</hi> Job 41. 1, 2, 3, 4, 10, &amp;c. <hi>Canſt thou draw out</hi> Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>with an hook, or his tongue with a cord, which thou letteſt down? canſt thou put an hook into his noſe, or bore his jaw through with a thorn? will he make many ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions unto thee? will he ſpeak ſoft words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee? will he make a covenant with thee? wilt thou take him for a Servant for ever? None is ſo fierce that dare ſtir him up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, (1.) If this be truly the State of any Family; Good God! to what a paſs has the neglect of Family-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment brought us? Let the Perverſeneſs of thy Family cauſe thee to reflect on thine own ſinful Neglects. Thou ſhouldeſt have
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51600:34"/> buckled ſooner to this Buſineſs thy ſelf, and have bent theſe Twigs when greener. Be humbled for thy great Failings and Neglects in this Particular, and be ſenſible, that the State of thy Family ſpeaks the greater need of what I have been urging.</p>
               <p>(2.) Make a prudent and compaſſionate, but withal effectual uſe of your Authority; yea, if need be, call in the Miniſter's help. Theſe obſtinate Perſons muſt at leaſt be roundly talked with. And it may be after all, thou may'ſt find the Event better than thou imagineſt. Yea, this Ordinance will be a means of engaging your Affections one to another. I ſpeak it from ſome meaſure of Experience.</p>
               <p>(3). Begin with thoſe few you can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and it may be others may afterward comply; if from no better Principle, yet for very Shame.</p>
               <p>(4.) If any remain obſtinate, after all compaſſionate Endeavours and Forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, remove them, and get better in their room. Say, as <hi>David, Depart from me, ye evil-doers, for I will keep the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of my God,</hi> Pſal. 119. 115. <hi>A froward heart ſhall depart from me; I will not know a wicked Perſon. Mine eyes ſhall be upon the faithful of the land, that they may dwell with me: he that walketh in a perfect way, he ſhall ſerve me,</hi> Pſal. 101. 4, 6. Reſolve, as good <hi>Joſhua, As for me and my houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:51600:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Some, peradventure, may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>We have not obſerved Catechiſing to do any good; and therefore it is as well there be none at all, as to no purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, (1.) I have already proved <hi>Catechiſing</hi> an Ordinance of God, and have mentioned ſome of the many Benefits of it; and now I caution thee to take heed, that thou art not found guilty of bearing falſe-witneſs againſt ſo neceſſary and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial an Ordinance. Thou art not to <hi>bear falſe-witneſs againſt thy Neighbour,</hi> Exod. 20. 16. much leſs againſt thy GOD.</p>
               <p>(2.) If the Abuſe of Ordinances by ſome, yea, the generality, were a good Plea againſt the lawful Uſe of them, we might, for the ſame reaſon, caſt off all the Ordinances of the Goſpel, as the <hi>Word,</hi> in the private reading and publick miniſtry of it; <hi>Prayer, Sacraments,</hi> &amp;c. Nay, if we may uſe nothing that others abuſe, we muſt abandon Meat, Drink, Cloathing; yea, and Life it ſelf: For too many make an ill Uſe of all theſe.</p>
               <p>(3.) It may be, where thou obſerveſt ſo little fruit, there has been ſome great fault in the Performance of this Duty. It has not been ſet upon ſo ſolemnly and ſeriouſly, ſo underſtandingly and judiciouſly. It may be, it hath not been preceded with Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, accompanied with Prayer, nor fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with future Watchfulneſs. Can we expect God ſhould regard our Duties, when
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51600:35"/> we our ſelves do not duly regard them?</p>
               <p>(4.) Thou art not, thou canſt not be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that no good has been done hereby. There may be good, yea, much and great Good done by this Ordinance, tho' it come not under thy Cognizance. Some one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may have been brought hereby to know God, to bow the Knee in ſecret to him, and lay hold of his Covenant. Theſe things may be, though thou haſt no particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of them: yea, if this Ordinance has but promoted one good Thought among all thoſe that have been under it, this alone were enough to confute this Objection.</p>
               <p>(5.) The Time employed in Catechiſing, might have been worſe ſpent, and more Sin then, and at other times committed againſt God. Now it is a great thing to prevent, though it were but one Sin, one Act of Diſhonour againſt the Great God; and it cannot reaſonably be thought, but that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing hath prevented many.</p>
               <p>(6.) <hi>Duty</hi> is <hi>Duty,</hi> and muſt be done; and whatever effect it has upon others, yet the Performance of it will tend to our Comfort and profit, both here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. If we have, with the Diſciples, <hi>been fiſhing long, and caught nothing,</hi> Luke 5. 5, 6. yet at the Command of our Lord, we muſt continue to <hi>let down the Net,</hi> and may, at laſt, <hi>have a plentiful draught.</hi> But however, if God commands, we muſt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, tho' it be a dry Stick, all our days:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51600:35"/> And as he comforted himſelf, <hi>though Iſrael be not gathered, yet ſhall we be glorious in the eyes of the Lord, and our reward ſhall be with him,</hi> Iſa. 46. 4, 5.</p>
               <p>(7.) It is certain, much good has been done by Catechiſing: Many Miniſters and People, Parents and Children, Maſters and Servants, have ſet their Seal to it: And I wiſh, That as any receive Benefit by this Ordinance, they would give their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, for the further Confutation of this Objection.</p>
               <p>(8.) If any have abuſed this, (as what Ordinance is there that ſome have not abuſed?) their Judgment will be the greater, but the Duty is no whit the leſs: Yea, let me add, Thy Judgment and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation will be the greater, if after this Admonition, thou either neglecteſt or trifleſt with this Ordinance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Some, peradventure, may yet object, <hi>Here is more adoe about this Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than need: Many have gone to Heaven, who never ſet up Catechiſing in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, nor were Catechiſed there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, (1.) If thou only careſt to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Heaven, but not to obey God, thou art never like to come there. <hi>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt is the Author of eternal ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to them that obey him,</hi> Heb. 5. 9.</p>
               <p>(2.) Many that have committed great Sins, as well as omitted great Duties, have at laſt, tho' with great Difficulty, got to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51600:36"/> Heaven; but this ſhould no more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us to omit the one, than commit the other; and we may pay dear for either.</p>
               <p>(3.) The whole Chriſtian World, at this day, groans under the ſad Conſequences of the paſt, and preſent Neglects of this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. What a Floud of Atheiſm, Irreligion, Unbelief, Hypocriſie, Formality, Error, Hereſie, Schiſm, Profaneneſs, and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries of all kinds, has broken in at this Gap, The Neglect of Family Government, and Inſtruction? This has made that part of the Chriſtian World that calls it ſelf Reformed; a kind of Hell. Tho' God has yet reſerved to himſelf a little Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>(4.) Family-Reformation and Order is one of the ſpecial Works and Duties of this Day, and God will leaſt bear with the Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects of that. It is hoped that thoſe Times are even at the Door, when according as the Lord hath both promiſed, and ſworn, <hi>the whole Earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea.</hi> Numb. 14. 21. Iſai. 11. 9. when not only the Houſe of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but all the Families of the Nations ſhall be brought to know and acknowledge the Lord. And ſurely if Family-Reformation were more promoted, it would have a Tendency toward; yea, look like the beginning of that great Work. Now we ſhould be like thoſe Men of <hi>Iſſachar, who were men that</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:51600:36"/> 
                  <hi>had underſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do,</hi> 1 Chron. 12. 32.</p>
               <p>(5.) God now expects this from you, more eſpecially, who has done more for you than for others. You have been (like <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>'s Fleece) wet with the Dew of Heaven, when all the Ground about you has been dry. You have been in a lightſome <hi>Goſhen,</hi> others in <hi>Egyptian</hi> Darkneſs; Darkneſs that may be felt. You have been watered like Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> others have been like the barren Mountains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> upon whom no Rain nor Dew deſcends; and therefore can yield no Fields of Offerings. Yea, you have the Servants of God to direct, aſſiſt, and encourage you, not only in the Temple-Work of Publick Worſhip, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in making your Private Dwelling-Places Habitations for the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore huſh all <hi>Objections,</hi> and <hi>Diſputes;</hi> up and be Doing, and the Lord will be with you.</p>
               <p>Thus I have, as a Spiritual Shepherd, been feeding both the Sheep and Lambs of the Flock. I have urged upon Parents and Governours of Families their Duty, both with reſpect to themſelves, and the Souls under their Charge. I have alſo admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Children, Servants, and the Governed Part of Families, what they ought to do: I have ſuggeſted Motives unto each, and endeavoured to remove the Objections of all. If any reſolve yet to remain obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51600:37"/> and ungovernable, God himſelf will, ſooner or later, ſpeak to them at another rate than I can do. The Lord hath ſaid, of him who <hi>cometh to enquire of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but ſetteth up his Idols in his heart, and putteth the ſtumbling-block of his iniquity before his face,</hi> that he <hi>will anſwer him by himſelf,</hi> Ezek. 14. 7. And to the <hi>froward,</hi> he will <hi>ſhew himſelf froward,</hi> Pſal. 18. 26. But if you will, on all hands, perform your Duty, as you have been directed, God will be glorified, your Miniſters will be comforted over you, and Your Selves may reap the benefit of it, here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>I ſhall, finally, leave with you two places of Scripture, and conclude.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Know therefore this day, and conſider it in thine heart, that the Lord he is God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven above, and upon the earth beneath: there is none elſe.—Thou ſhalt keep there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his ſtatutes, and his commandments which I command thee this day, that it may go well with thee, and with thy children after thee,</hi> Deut. 4. 39, 40.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And they, whether they will hear, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will forbear, yet ſhall know that there hath been a Prophet among them,</hi> Ezek. 2. 5.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51600:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
